# RYKER REED SOFTWARE ENGINEER

**♥** Los Angeles, CA

in ryker-reed

n reedr3

I am passionate about using my skills to create beautiful and meaningful things that can effect positive change in the lives of those around me. I am particularly excited to contribute to educational technologies and technologies that can directly benefit marginalized communities. I have an extensive background in Linguistics and analytical research. I enjoy tackling complex problems and working in environments that constantly challenge me.

#### Skills

#### **FRONTEND**

**JavaScript** 

**jQuery** 

XALA

HTML

CSS

React

**BACKEND** 

Ruby

Rails

ActiveRecord

PostgreSQL

**SQLite** 

**Action Cable** 

Python

**PERSONAL** 

**Public Speaking** 

Advocacy

**Technical Writing** 

**Teaching** 

### Education

Massachusetts Institute of Technology BS Linguistics 2014 Dev Bootcamp Computer Software Engineering 2016

Boston University MA Linguistics 2017

## Projects

Game the Progress

Sep 2016 - Oct 2016

Created Game the Progress, a web app designed to give teachers a platform to custom build and play game quizzes with multiple students. Worked with a team of four other developers over an eight day period to go from initial pitch to functional product. Worked primarily on the backend ActiveRecord associations and Action Cable WebSockets interface.

My Linguistic Facts Oct 2016

Created and published a skill for the Amazon Alexa skills store. This skill allows Alexa to dynamically respond to requests for information about linguistics, spanning many sub-fields including syntax, phonology, morphology, semantics, historical linguistics, language acquisition, and constructed languages.

EmpathyQuest Nov 2016 - Present

Created EmpathyQuest, an educational adventure role playing game which introduces players to complex cultural concepts such as privilege, oppression, and microaggressions. Created the app using Javascript, Phaser, Intel XDK, and Cordova.

Pensieve Nov 2016 - Present

Created Pensieve, a web app designed to aid and increase productivity by allowing users to efficiently compartmentalize tasks. Tasks can be tagged with the timeframe in which they need to be completed as well as how much effort will be required so that users can search and sort tasks by these tags. Created the app using Rails, ActiveRecord, Javascript, React, HTML, and CSS.

## Experience

Massachusetts Transgender Political Coalition Legal Intern, Boston, MA Aug 2014 - Dec 2014

Researched national and state gender identity policies. Wrote legal briefs for Massachusetts Senate Bill 2407 (passed July 2016), amending the prohibition on discrimination in public accommodations under the Massachusetts Civil Rights Act to include gender identity.

MIT Linguistics Department

Jan 2012 - Sep 2013

Nov 2012 - Mar 2016

Undergraduate Researcher, Singapore and Cambridge, MA

Led a research team examining the psychological effects of a "learning mindset" on language learning abilities at Singapore University of Technology and Design. Developed and taught an experimental curriculum on artificially constructed language.

#### Activities and Volunteering

MIT Splash Program

Teacher

Created curriculum and taught classes on Linguistics and on Gender Beyond the Binary to middle and high school students.

MIT and Dev Bootcamp

Workshop Leader Nov 2013 - Present

Led "How to be a Trans Ally" workshops for students, staff, and faculty. Created educational content and interactive activities. Spoke about personal experiences, led group discussions, and provided suggestions for making MIT and Dev Bootcamp safer, more inclusive spaces.

Boston Beantown Softball League

First Baseman Apr 2013 - Jul 2016

MIT Gender Fluidity Group

President May 2013 - Jun 2014

MIT Figure Skating Club

Executive Member Oct 2012 - Jun 2014

Awards

MIT Burchard Scholar for Excellence in the Humanities MIT School of Humanities, Arts, and Social Sciences

Feb 2013

MIT Louis Kampf Writing Prize in Women's and Gender Studies MIT Women's and Gender Studies Department Wrote a science fiction novella.

May 2014